She became a singer because it was the only thing she could do. She
became a star because it was the only way she could do it.
Coal Miner's Daughter is a music, drama film directed by Michael Apted.
Biography of Loretta Lynn, a country and western
singer that came from poverty to fame.
Loretta Lynn, played by Sissy Spacek.
'Mooney' Lynn, played by Tommy Lee Jones.
Ted Webb, played by Levon Helm.
Patsy Cline, played by Beverly D'Angelo.
Lee Dollarhide, played by William Sanderson.
'Clary' Webb, played by Phyllis Boyens.
Coal Miner's Daughter is a 1980 American biographical musical film
directed by Michael Apted and written by Tom Rickman.
It follows the story of country music singer Loretta Lynn from her early teen years in a poor family
and getting married at 15 to her rise as one of the most influential country musicians.
Based on Lynn's 1976 biography of the same name by George
Vecsey, the film stars Sissy Spacek as Lynn.
Tommy Lee Jones, Beverly D'Angelo and Levon Helm
are featured in supporting roles.
Ernest Tubb, Roy Acuff, and Minnie Pearl make cameo appearances as themselves.
A film on Lynn's life was intended to be made
since the release of the biography.
Production for the film began in March 1979, and Lynn herself chose Spacek to portray her on
screen after seeing a photograph of her, despite being unfamiliar with her films.
The film's soundtrack featured all of Lynn's hit singles, which were all sung by Spacek, as well as Patsy Cline's
"Sweet Dreams" sung by D'Angelo and Cline's "Back in Baby's Arms" sung by Spacek and D'Angelo in a duet.
The soundtrack reached the top 40 on the Billboard 200 chart and was
certified gold by the Recording Industry Association of America.
Universal Pictures released Coal Miner's Daughter theatrically on March 7, 1980.
The critical consensus on Rotten Tomatoes calls it "a solidly affecting story".
The film grossed $67.18 million in North America against a budget of $15
million, becoming the seventh highest-grossing film of 1980.
The film received seven nominations at the 53rd Academy Awards,
including for Best Picture, with Spacek winning Best Actress.
At the 38th Golden Globe Awards, it garnered four nominations and won two; Best
Motion Picture – Musical or Comedy and Best Actress  (for Spacek).
The film is considered "culturally, historically or aesthetically significant" by the Library of
Congress and was selected to be preserved in the United States National Film Registry in 2019.
The film explores themes of country music, kentucky, female
friendship, biography, washington state.
The tone is emotional.